בטוב. Betov. Today's דף daf is ע"ב, Ayin Bet, 72 עמוד ב',
amud bet, 73, but we are on ע"ב Ayin Bet and we
pick up right after the משנה. mishnah. The משנה mishnah now, this
is I should say that you know, it's often when people do
סנהדרין Sanhedrin that they do the eighth פרק, perek, particularly in schools,
because well maybe you want to teach the kids first about בן
סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh and you better behave. But actually I
think the reason that they do it is because of the משניות
mishnayot that we have just begun and that we're going to do.
The whole idea about the person who comes in a, you know,
הבא במחתרת, haba b'machteret, who comes through a tunnel and the right
of self-defense,
and that raises very fascinating issues and then we're going to see
that into the next משנה, mishnah, the next דף, daf, that has
to deal with, you know, with also somebody who's running after somebody
and that you should intervene and to save the life of the
person who is being chased after, and when would you apply that
cases of murder to cases of rape and so on and, you
know, comes up as we'll see later today, the whole issue about
a woman who's having a hard time giving birth and the child
is threatening her life, the fetus is threatening her life, you know,
so there it's it raises very big philosophical and halachic and, you
know, practical types of questions. So our משנה, mishnah, and of course
the link is the fact that the opening that we just had
a משנה mishnah that said a בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh
was נידון על שם סופו, nidon al shem sofo, is being judged
because of the תורה Torah looking into his future. And so similarly
it's dealing with the case in the תורה Torah that says, you
know, if somebody comes through a tunnel והוכה ומת אין לו דמים
v'huka va-met ein lo damim and he is smitten, he is hit
by the owner, presumably the owner, then there will be no blood,
the owner will not be held liable, but once he comes out
of the tunnel, at least this is the literal meaning of the
פסוקים, pesukim, אם זרחה השמש עליו דמים לו, im zeracha hashemesh alav
damim lo, and if the sun shines on him then it will
be considered blood, it would be considered murder and presumably the meaning
is, you know, that when he's in the tunnel there, he, you
know, he is representing a threat to the owner's life, this owner
has to act, is acting out of a perceived threat to his
life. Once he's out of the tunnel and presumably running away, then
there's no longer a perceived threat to his life and he cannot
and he cannot be killed. So that becomes implicitly the right of
self-defense, even if it requires using lethal force. And that's the משנה,
mishnah, הבא במחתרת, haba b'machteret, just to re-read the משנה, mishnah, right,
נידון על שם סופו, nidon al shem sofo, is judged because of
his end. Now what does that mean, his end? That's different than
what we had by the בן סורר ומורה. Ben Sorer u-Moreh. It's
not because, oh, this guy's going to turn out to be a
terrible
person and we're judging him now so that he doesn't leave a
life, live a life of crime, like that's sort of what the
בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u-Moreh is. This is something completely different.
As the גמרא Gemara says,
we understand that because of what he's prepared to do, he understands
that the owner will defend his property and that he might have
to use force and so on, and because of what he is
prepared to do, that allows us to see this case right now
in front of us as a threat to the person's life. So
it's really a very different type of נידון על שם סופו, nidon
al shem sofo, right? We are not saying that now you're a
רשע rasha because of what you'll do in the future, we have
to protect you from what you'll do in the future. We're saying
that right now because of our understanding of what might transpire, you
are presenting a threat, you know, to the owner's life and the
owner is entitled to use, or maybe has to use, whatever, entitled
to use lethal force to defend himself. So it really is something
very much in the context of self-defense and when is it legitimate
to perceive it and to understand it as a threat to life.
But the problem is, or the interesting thing is, and this is
what we're going to continue with today, is that the next line
says הבא במחתרת ושיבר את החבית אם יש לו דמים חייב אם
אין לו דמים פטור. haba b'machteret v'shibar et hachavit, im yesh lo
damim chayav, im ein lo damim patur. If he broke something in
his way of coming into the tunnel, if he's in a case
where
it's יש לו דמים, yesh lo damim, so that you cannot kill
him, then he has to pay for things that he breaks. But
if it's in a context where he can be killed, אין לו
דמים, ein lo damim, he doesn't have to pay. I do wonder
if there is a little play on words going on here because
דמים damim also means money. So, although I think it means that,
I have to find out if the משנה mishnah ever uses it
that way. I remember that my first trip to Israel when I
went to ישיבה yeshiva and I was 17 and I had never
done any spoken Hebrew, you know, and it was, you know, I
only knew all my Hebrew from the גמרא Gemara and from תנ"ך
Tanakh I guess anyway, so I come off and I am saying
something like יש לך דמים yesh l'cha damim or אין לי דמים,
ein li damim, they say, what are you talking about? So anyway,
so I do wonder if there's a little bit of a play
on words, because when it's יש לו דמים, yesh lo damim, when
it would be spilling blood, when you cannot, don't have a right
to kill him, then he has to pay money, then the same
יש לו דמים yesh lo damim then like you have to pay
for the things that you broke. If אין לו דמים, ein lo
damim, if you wouldn't be spilling blood, then he doesn't have to
pay any money for things that he breaks. The principle there seems
to be a principle of, right, קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam leh
b'drabba mineh. If somebody does an act that they're liable the death
penalty, then they you cannot give them a any other punishment that
that is incurred during that same act. Even if they're not going
to get the death penalty, a classic example would be somebody goes
ahead
and murders somebody, shoots an arrow and ruins their nice clothes, their
nice shirt because of the blood that's spilt on the arrow by
shooting the arrow at them or shooting the bullet at them, even
if there are no witnesses,
even if he did it by accident בשוגג, b'shogeg, since it's the
type of an act that would be punishable by the death penalty,
he doesn't have to pay. So the problem is applying that idea
here, because this person is not liable to the death penalty. This
person cannot be brought to court and after the fact be
executed. The right of self-defense is an immediate act to protect the
potential victim. It is not a judgment that is being issued against
this person. And nevertheless, the משנה mishnah and the גמרא gemara as
we're about to see, apply to it this principle of קים ליה
בדרבא מיניה. kim lei b'derabba minei. So one can draw one of
two conclusions. The normal conclusion that is drawn is we see that
the principle of קים ליה בדרבא מיניה kim lei b'derabba minei is
broader than we thought. It's not limited to cases of a court-imposed
punishment. That if the court, if it's an act that the court
could impose punishment X, then they can't impose punishment Y. It's actually
a more broader principle, at least when it comes to things that
are deserving of death, that in the context
of perpetrating an act, of doing an act that somebody would be
entitled to kill you for whatever reason, whether the act is something
that would entitle a court to execute you later or an act
that would entitle somebody to kill this person to defend the potential
victim, nevertheless, in that type of a horrific act that somehow you're
putting your life on the line or you're forfeiting your life, no
other liability can be incurred. It's not just a הלכה halacha about
בית דין. beit din. It's a הלכה halacha that the power of
that act
overwhelms the significance of anything else. Who cares that you broke some
stuff? You were go ahead and you were forfeiting your life. That's
all we can see right now is that you're now forfeiting your
life and somebody could kill you right now to protect the victim.
So that's one way to understand it, not in the context of
בית דין. beit din. I want to put out a different way,
which I think emerges very much from the גמרא gemara that we're
going to see today, which is normally not said because it's weird,
but I think it's implicit, and it is that rather than to
see this as just a case of self-defense,
to almost see the case of self-defense as, if you're defending yourself,
then it's sort of like עביד אינש דינא לנפשיה. avid inish dina
l'nafshei. That actually ties in very much. If you're going to break
into my house and if I'm stealing something, the example is I've
stolen something of yours and I'm refusing to give it back. You
can break into my house, knock my teeth out, grab your thing
and take it back, because you have the right עביד אינש דינא
לנפשיה. avid inish dina l'nafshei. You can go ahead and do vigilante
justice for yourself to protect your own
property. That's a similar idea, or I can certainly use force to
keep you off of my property. That is if you're
trespassing and you won't just listen to me. I can go ahead
and literally hit you with a shovel or something to get you
off my property. So in the right to protect your own property,
you're allowed to use force, and some ראשונים rishonim understand that it's
the same issue. Do you understand that just as a right to
self-protection, or do you understand it as you are operating as a
representative of the court in that capacity? The way the רמב"ם Rambam
says why is עביד אינש דינא לנפשיה, avid inish dina l'nafshei, the
רמב"ם Rambam says because
מעיקר הדין m'ikar hadin one person can be a
דיין. dayan. So you're your own דיין. dayan. Somehow you're like a
representative of the court in protecting your property, and somebody else can't
be, but you
can. So it's very possible to understand that there's an implicit understanding
here that the same is true with protecting your life. Your life
is at risk, and nobody else is around to protect it. You
can
operate as a representative of the court, of the legal system, to
protect your life. And maybe if somebody else חזי chazei somebody's life
is at risk, and we're going to get to this case of
רודף, rodef, and intervenes to protect the victim, then he's acting as
a representative of the court because the court isn't around, the police
aren't around, so it doesn't become vigilante. It becomes you become deputized
to actually be because we still need it to be operating within
a system of
law to be protecting the person and to be representing the legal
system. So if that's the case, then when this person is liable
to the death penalty,
not liable to the death penalty, if this person can be killed
to protect the victim when he's in the
מחתרת, machteret, it's not just seen as a right of self-defense, it's
seen as the court, the legal system can intervene to take his
life to protect the potential victim. And if that's true, then it's
more similar to the classic idea of קים ליה בדרבא מיניה. kim
lei b'derabba minei. This guy is doing an act that the legal
system, it won't execute him afterwards, but that the legal system will
actually kill him or execute him right now to protect the victim.
So I think that the using the idea that you're not liable
for money. damages is either an expansion of the principle of קים
ליה Kimlei to go outside of the idea of court imposed punishments,
or more interesting for us, it's a reshaping of the understanding of
why you can use lethal force. Not just protecting yourself, but actually
being seen as a type of operating for the by as a
representative of the court, you know, to actually protect either yourself or
somebody else who is the potential victim. But it's almost like the
court is actually judging this person. Alright, so those are two very
interestingly interesting models. And with that in mind, that was all הקדמה
hakdama but a very important הקדמה. hakdama. Let's take a look where
we're up to, four lines down in the גמרא Gemara אמר רב
Amar Rav by the asterisk. So רבא Rava just introduced it by
saying, you know, we since the guy will use lethal force if
the owner tries to protect his property, therefore it's self-defense. And now
we have the following statement. אמר רב, Amar Rav, yes.
Because it says התורה אמרה אם בא להורגך השכם להורגו. HaTorah amrah
im ba lehorgecha hashkem lehorgo. Right, that's the Torah state it like
this? Is there a פסוק? Pasuk?
Well, okay, you know what, let me just read it, since it's
only four lines. We'll read it from the beginning of the גמרא.
Gemara. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מאי טעמא דמחתרת? Mai taama de'machteret? What's
the reason? What does this mean, יתנו השם סופו? yitnu hashem sofo?
חזקה, Chazakah, we can assume אין אדם מעמיד עצמו על ממונו, ein
adam ma'amid atzmo al mamono, a person will not stand by when
somebody is coming to take his money. והאי מימר אמר אי אזלינא
קאי לאפאי ולא שביק לי vehai meimar amar ee azlina kaei le'apai
velo shavik li and the גנב ganev who's coming in knows that
if the owner... right, this is why like you know armed robbery
is so much you know is so much treated so much differently
than when it's not armed because there's an understanding of why are
you going in with a gun to rob this guy's house, right?
The reason you're going in with a gun is because if the
guy puts up any resistance you're planning on killing him. Okay, so
it's a very different type of an
act. So here the gun, it's an issue of the gun is
an indication of how far you're willing to go. Okay, and that
you're prepared to use lethal force if necessary. והאי מימר אמר אי
אזלינא קאי
לאפאי ולא שביק לי, vehai meimar amar ee azlina kaei le'apai velo
shavik li, if he you know if he if I go he
stands in front of me, I have to confront the owner, he
won't allow me to just take his property. ואי קאי לאפאי קטילנא
ליה, ve'ee kaei le'apai katlina lei, so therefore if he if he
opposes me, I will be prepared to kill him. Okay, so because
of the gun we assume that you are prepared to use lethal
force if necessary. והתורה אמרה, veHaTorah amrah, the Torah says, אם בא
להורגך השכם להורגו. im ba lehorgecha hashkem lehorgo. If somebody is coming
to kill you, you beat him to the punch, you go ahead
and you kill him, you protect yourself. Okay and you know there's
an interesting discussion, is this a רשות reshus or a מצוה? mitzvah?
You know, most but most understand it as a מצוה mitzvah also
for yourself and for others. Okay, but 'no I'm going to be
a צדיק tzaddik I'm going to let him kill me I'm not
going to' right, it seems like it's actually a מצוה, mitzvah, it's
the language of the גמרא Gemara אם בא להורגך השכם להורגו, im
ba lehorgecha hashkem lehorgo,
right? You have an obligation, somebody else would have an obligation to
save the victim and you have an obligation to act to save
yourself. I do want to say within that obligation that there's a
limitation which we've seen before in the גמרא Gemara which is יכול
להצילו באחד מאבריו. yakhol lehatzilo be'echad me'evarav.
If you reasonably could have stopped him without killing him, right then
then you're not allowed to kill him and if so it would
be you know I mean it would be like manslaughter it wouldn't
be like whatever murder etc however it would be judged in a
court. Okay, but you have to but then the question is in
that moment of fright and all those things you know we have
to assess like what means that it was reasonably possible for you
to do without killing him. Right, so that's always a question you
know courts are always dealing with. But at least that's an important
limitation. The other interesting thing is we don't say that you have
an obligation to say take my money I'd rather you know I
don't want to have to kill you just take my money. Right,
that you're not obligated to say like the story with the חפץ
חיים Chofetz Chaim you know somebody breaks into his house and steals
his stuff and then he's running after the guy and he's saying
אני מוחל, Ani mochel, you know? So you have no obligation to
say אני מוחל Ani mochel I don't want to have to kill
you take my stuff. Like no, it starts that you have a
right to protect your own property, right? And then once you have
a right to protect your own property you have a right to
protect your own life. So those are like really interesting foundations upon
which this is built. Now you know Michal asks where is the
Torah saying השכם להורגו? hashkem lehorgo? So one place it's saying it
is it's implicitly saying it here, meaning we are revealing what the
underlying principle is why אין לו דמים. ein lo damim. The other
place it's saying it which we are going to see in the
next משנה Mishnah is by the case of נערה מאורסה, Na'arah me'orasah,
a woman who is raped, a betrothed woman where the Torah says
אין מושיע לה. ein moshia lah. She cried out and there was
nobody to save her. הא יש לה מושיע, ha'yesh lah moshia, which
means if there was somebody who could have saved her and he
heard her cries, he had an obligation to save her even if
it would have required taking the life of the rapist. Okay, so
from נערה מאורסה Na'arah me'orasah we're going to see there's also a
similar idea that that's not murder, that's another and we're going to
have to figure out what are the crimes or what are the
sins that you're entitled to do that. But that the Torah is
telling us you have a right and an obligation to go out
and protect the potential victim. Okay, so that's the basic principle a
very different על שם סופו al shem sofo than the בן סורר
ומורה. Ben sorer u'moreh. And now we get to this issue about
not having to pay money.
אמר רב amar Rav said רב, Rav, הבא במחתרת, haba bamachteres, somebody
who is coming through the tunnel, ונטל כלים ויצא פטור, venatal kelim
veyatza patur, and he went ahead and he took vessels, you know,
he stole, he succeeded, right? He took the guy's TV, and then
he left the tunnel, he's exempt from giving back the TV. Okay,
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? בדמי קננהו. bidamei kanahu. Again,
I think it's a play on words. He purchased it with his
blood. Also, he purchased it with, I think it's a play, purchased
it with money, you know, but not really with money. He purchased
it with his own blood. Since he could have been killed, he
doesn't have to pay for what he did.
Okay, ואמר רבא, ve'amar Rava, and we just discussed all that whole
principle of קים ליה. kam lei. רבא Rava says, you know what,
מסתברא מילתא דרב, mistavra milsa deRav, it makes sense to limit the
statement of רב Rav בשיברי. beshivrei. If the vessel got broke, if
the TV, he broke the TV. Because if he broke the TV,
what would he have to do? Were he to have to be,
you know, pay the, you know, make restitution, he'd have to pay
the owner. So that's a debt, that's an obligation. Okay, and there
we would say he doesn't have that monetary debt, which was incurred
in the process of committing, you know, of this crime that his
life was, that he could have been killed.
דליתנהו, delasnehu, because then the TV is no longer around.
אבל נטל לא. aval natal lo. But if he just took the
TV,
then, okay, we're not going to impose any punishment on him, but
he's got my TV. So give me back my TV. If my
TV had rolled into your yard, you'd have to give it back.
It's not that we're imposing a punishment, it's just it's still my
TV in your hands. So if the TV isn't around and it's
a question do you owe me money, the answer is no. You
were, you could have been killed, you did an act that forfeited
your life, there's no going to be no punishment even a monetary,
you know, obligation imposed on you. But that's not the same as
why do you have a right to own my TV? It's my
TV, give it back. Okay, so that's what רב Rav says which
makes a lot of sense. But אמר amar so, I mean רבא
Rava says, to limit the statement of רב. Rav. But now the
גמרא, Gemara, it's a גזירת אלהים, gezeiras Elohim, it's a little question
as to whether the גמרא Gemara is responding this or רבא Rava
himself is saying it, but in, but by oath, אמר רבא אפילו
נטל. amar Rava afilu natal. I'm wondering your English translations, do they
still have this as what רבא, Rava, as what רבא'ס Rava's saying?
You know,
רבא Rava says,
it's רבא'ס, Rava's, רבא'ס Rava's still saying. It makes sense to limit
רב'ס Rav's statement to when the TV broke. But in fact, by
oath, you know, taking an oath, you know, but I swear to
the fact that he actually went so far to say even when
it got broken. Even when, excuse me, it was still around. So
even though this statement is crazy, like would be crazy in my
mind, where the TV still, is still in its, you know, in
its right shape. But it's, but it's, but it seems that רב
Rav really was saying that. רב Rav really said that even if
the TV is still there, the גנב ganav doesn't have to give
it back. Now why is that? Okay, דהא יש לו דמים וניאנסו
חייב, deha yesh lo damei vene'ensu chayav, and this is what רב'ס
Rav's reasoning is. Because רב Rav says look, if it was a
case where the person was יש לו דמים, yesh lo damei, where
the person
was, could not have, you know, would not have been risking his
life, okay, וניאנסו, vene'ensu, and something happened to the TV. So a
normal case of a גנב, ganav, so חייב, chayav, he'd have to
pay. אלמא ברשותיה קיימי. almana birshuso kaimei.
So that shows me in a normal case of a גנב, ganav,
what happens? Okay, a normal case of a גנב, ganav, somebody steals
something, and then something happens which was not in his control. Like
I went ahead and I, you know, stole David's TV, and then
a, something completely uncontrollable happened, there was a flood, it flooded all
our homes, it would have even flooded David's home, and the TV
broke. So why do I have to pay David? I say it
wasn't my fault that the TV broke, right? Why do I have
to pay him? So the reason is, the explanation here is that
the, the way it's explained why a גנב ganav has to make
restitution if the thing isn't around even if it wasn't the גנב'ס
ganav's fault, is because we say the moment I took David's TV,
it's like I, it's like I owned it. And what at that
moment, I, I became obligated to him the value of that TV.
So this is an interesting question, like if we learn, if by
בבא קמא Bava Kamma it's always the question: when does the obligation
of compensation kick in as opposed to the obligation to return the
object? The natural way to think about it is, I steal the
TV, I'm obligated to return it. If it's not around, then that
obligation to return it is replaced by an obligation of compensation. Okay,
and then, then you might ask questions, let's say it wasn't my
fault that it broke. Okay, but you could say tough luck, whatever,
since you stole it, you're always going to be obligated to compensate
once you can't return. But nevertheless to think of it in two
stages. Okay, but before, while it's still around, it's still David's and
I'm obligated to return it. What the גמרא Gemara is saying is
no, the reason I would have to compensate, the only way to
explain why I would have to compensate even if it wasn't my
fault if it broke, is because from the very moment I took
it, I owed him money. I didn't owe him the TV. And
if the TV was still there, I could give him the TV
and get out of my monetary obligation. Maybe I would have to
first give him the TV. Whatever, but fundamentally from the moment I
took it I owed him money. And that's why if something breaks,
if it breaks even not due to my fault, it doesn't matter
whether it's my fault or not, the monetary obligation kicked in at
the beginning. Ah, if we say that, then somebody who's בא במחתרת
Ba b'machteret and steals David's TV is, if we conceptualize what happens
at that moment as not that he has to give back the
TV. What happens at that moment is he now owns the TV
and just owes David the money, right? If that's how we conceptualize
what happens, then okay, he doesn't owe David any money because he's,
you know, his life is at, you know, he's forfeiting his life.
And the fact David will come say give me back my TV,
it's my TV, he'll say it's not your TV, it became my
TV the minute I took it. I just owed you money. But
because I was risking my life, I don't owe you money. Okay,
so that's explaining it. It's strange, right? Normally of course we would
say, what are you talking about? The TV is still there, it's
my TV, give it back. Okay, but this is the way רבא
Rava is explaining why רב Rav is saying, would say an extreme
statement that רבא Rava doesn't agree with. But what is behind רב's
Rav's extreme statement? Okay, but let me just read it again. אפילו
נטלו, Afilu netalo, even if it's still there and it's in its
right shape, דהא יש לו דמים באונס וחייב. De-ha yesh lo damim
be-oness ve-chayav. If it's a normal case of a גנב Ganav who's
not risking his life, okay, and some accident happens after he steals
it, he has to compensate. אלמא ברשותיה קני, Alma birshutei kanei, you
see conceptually what we're saying is that from the moment it's taken,
it's owned by the גנב. Ganav. And instead what the גנב Ganav
just owes is money. So הכא נמי ברשותיה קני. Hacha nami birshutei
kanei. Here too he owns the TV and the only thing is
an obligation of money and the money obligation goes away. So the
גמרא Gemara says ולא היא. Ve-lo hee. So presumably this is still
all רבא Rava talking. This is what's behind רב's Rav's statement, but
that does not make any sense. I don't agree with that at
all. Okay, כי אוקימנא רחמנא ברשותיה, Ki ukimna rachmana birshutei,
under what circumstances did the תורה Torah say that the גנב Ganav
owns the TV? לענין אונסין, Le-inyan onsin, for the purpose of saying
that if something happens to it, you know, you have to pay
back. Okay, אבל לענין מקני, Aval le-inyan miknei, but in terms of
who actually owns the TV, ברשותא דמרא קאי, Birshuta de-marei kai, it's
in the,
it still belongs to the owner. And here's the analogy. מידי דהוה
אשואל, Midi de-hava a-shoel, like by somebody who borrows. If somebody borrowed,
if I borrowed David's TV and some uncontrollable accident happened to it,
even though I had no negligence, I have to pay. Why do
I have to pay if I borrow even if I'm completely blameless?
The principle is since I was getting all of the benefit in
that exchange, כל הנאה שלו, Kol hana'ah shelo, okay, since I was
getting all the benefit, I am accepting an absolute liability for anything
that goes wrong, even if it's not my fault. That's the principle
of a שואל, Shoel, right? So similarly by a גנב, Ganav, just
because a גנב Ganav is liable to compensate even when the TV
breaks due to no fault of his own, that does not mean
he owns the TV. Okay, it's no different than somebody who borrows
something. You took it, the תורה Torah puts on you, you know,
what's it called, strict liability. You are now going to have to
pay for it no matter what happens. Why? Because you stole the
darn thing, okay? But it is not because you own it. The
תורה Torah can put a liability on a person without any fault
of their own, and it doesn't mean that they own the TV,
that they own the object. So what he is saying is רב
Rav thinks you own the TV and you just have to pay
for it. So therefore in this case, since you don't have to
pay, you get to keep the TV. But that's not true. A
גנב Ganav does not own the object he stole. It's still the
owner's and he just has strict liability on it if anything goes
wrong. Okay, yes, Jenna? I was
just
wondering about when it says דמים, Damim, that means you didn't risk
your life? Correct, it would be considered spilling of blood to kill
him. Okay,
דמים
לו Damim lo or whatever it says. It says what's the פסוק?
Pasuk?
It says אם במחתרת ימצא הגנב והוכה ומת אין לו דמים,
Im ba-machteret yimatzei ha-ganav ve-hukah va-met ein
lo damim, okay, which means there's no spilling of blood for the
person who killed him. Okay, and then אם זרחה השמש עליו דמים
לו, Im zarchah ha-shemesh alav damim lo, which presumably means that he's
now running away and he's no longer a threat, דמים לו, Damim
lo, then יש לו דמים, Yesh lo damim, right?
And therefore it's spilling of blood. All right.
Okay, so now yes.
Just on his position that
if somebody survives and he owns the, he would own the object.
It's almost as if he's making him into a hero, you know,
it's like he put, you know, he like risked his
life and now
we're giving him a reward.
Right, I think I was trying to avoid that. I think that
was more how I was saying it, like I was saying he
risked his life, you know, or then I was switching to he
forfeited his life. Because you know the גמרא Gemara is just saying
does he have blood or not have blood, right? And I was
just trying to sort of find a good way to like encapsulate
that idea. But right, we're not saying, you're right, when you say
he risked his life it's usually... for a good cause. Right. So
that was—I said that, I think, and I corrected myself. You know,
he forfeited his life maybe, or you know, but okay.
Yes, one of the differences is actually a point noted about the
earlier part of the discussion whether some... whether somebody was willing to
murder or not and as opposed to רש"י, Rashi, the ר"ן Ran
says that there are burglars who would stop at that point rather
than—Well, the גמרא's Gemara going to get to that. I'll have to
look at the note, but the גמרא's Gemara going to get to
the question about whether every burglar is prepared to commit murder. Okay.
So that's going to be exactly the discussion that we're going to
get to. All right. So let's take a look. So okay. So
רבא Rava says I don't like רב's Rav statement, I would limit
it, but it seems that רב Rav is going to say an
extreme version of it.
Okay. תנן. Tnan. Now we're going to try to prove one way
or another way whether you can keep the thing, the גנב ganav
can keep the stuff that he stole even if it's still in
its original state. Okay. בא במחתרת ושיבר את החבית, ba bamachteret v'shibar
et hachavit, somebody coming in and broke the, you know, the barrel,
יש לו דמים yesh lo damim then he
חייב, chayav, if he is has blood, if, you know, you can't
kill him, then he has to pay for the barrel. אין לו
דמים, ein lo damim, if he's forfeiting his life, okay,
then פטור, patur, then he doesn't have to pay for what he
broke. Now טעמא דשיבר, ta'ama d'shibar, the reason is that the barrel
was broken, therefore he doesn't have to pay, no monetary punishment, you
know, sort of compensation is imposed on him. ובאין לו דמים פטור,
uve'ein lo damim patur, that's why when he has no blood, you
know, he's exempt. הנטל לא, hanoitel lo, but if he took the
barrel, he'd have to return it. That seems pretty implicit in our
משנה. Mishnah. So that's against רב's Rav statement.
The גמרא Gemara says no. הוא הדין דאפילו נטל, hu hadin d'afilu
natal, even if he took the barrel he wouldn't have to return
it according to רב. Rav. נמי. nami. והא דקתני שיבר את החבית,
v'had'katani shibar et hachavit, so why did the משנה Mishnah say he
broke the barrel? קמשמע לן דכי יש לו דמים kamashma lan d'chi
yesh lo damim to teach me that when he does have blood,
when, you know, he's not ready to commit murder, אף על גב
דשיבר נמי חייב, af al gav d'shibar nami chayav, even if, so
that when it's a normal גנב, ganav, not one who's forfeiting his
life, he would have to break it, even when he broke it,
he would have to pay the barrel even when he broke it,
not only when he took it. So like what's the חידוש chidush
about that? You're breaking into somebody's house and you break something, you
have to pay for it? It's like big, what's the חידוש? chidush?
So גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, of course. מזיק הוא, mazik hu,
you know, you're just somebody who's, you know,
a damager but anyway, somebody who's, you know, whatever, you're destroying somebody's
property.
הא קמשמע לן דאפילו שלא בכוונה, ha kamashma lan d'afilu shelo bekavana,
oh with an accident. I broke in your house and yes, I
did break the window to break in, but I accidentally broke your
vase, so I shouldn't have to pay for it. So גמרא Gemara
says come on, that's not a חידוש chidush either. מאי קמשמע לן,
mai kamashma lan, what is it teaching us? אדם מועד לעולם, adam
muad l'olam, that what, that you're always liable for damages you cause
even if you're not intentional? תנינא, tnineina, we taught in a משנה,
Mishnah, אדם מועד לעולם בין בשוגג בין במזיד בין באונס בין ברצון,
adam muad l'olam ben beshogeg ben bemezid ben be'ones ben beratzon, whether
willingly or intentionally, non-intentionally, willingly or unwillingly. Okay. So who needs a
משנה Mishnah to tell you that? So גמרא Gemara says קשיא, kashya,
all right, you're right, it's difficult. Now רש"י Rashi makes a point
to say here that it's a difference between קשיא kashya and תיובתא.
tiyuvta. Okay, I think people learn this like when they're early learning
גמרא. Gemara. קשיא kashya means you're right, the source doesn't work so
well with me, but it's not a contradiction to what I'm saying.
Because at the end of the day, the משנה Mishnah doesn't say
that if he took the barrel he'd have to return it. It's
just implicit. The משנה Mishnah says if he broke the barrel he
doesn't have to pay for it. So it implicitly is saying if
he took it he has to return it, but it's not saying
it explicitly. Maybe the משנה Mishnah is לאו דוקא, lav davka, even
if he took the barrel he wouldn't have to return it. So
that's why it's a difficulty to רב's Rav position, but it's not
a contradiction to רב's Rav position. Okay.
So that's one proof against רב, Rav, and now the גמרא Gemara
continues. מתיב רב
ביבי בר אביי, motiv Rav Bibi bar Abaye, רב ביבי בר אביי
Rav Bibi bar Abaye asked, okay, and this asks as a challenge
to רבא, Rava, this actually is a support of רב. Rav. הגונב
כיס בשבת חייב, hagonev kis b'shabbat chayav, somebody steals a wallet on
שבת, Shabbat, חייב, chayav, it's a classic קים ליה kim lei case.
You're doing an act of חילול שבת chillul Shabbat and incurring monetary
liability,
so you still have to pay that back. Why? שהרי נתחייב בגניבה
קודם שיבוא לידי איסור שבת. sheharei nitchayav bigniva kodem sheyavo lidei issur
Shabbat. In a normal case, somebody goes ahead and steals David's wallet,
the moment he takes David's wallet out of his house, out of
David's house or picks it up in David's house, he has now
stolen it. He's not מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat until he walks it
into the public domain. Okay, so they're not coming at the same
time. שהרי נתחייב בגניבה קודם שיבוא לידי איסור שבת. sheharei nitchayav bigniva
kodem sheyavo lidei issur Shabbat. היה מגרר ויוצא, haya megarer v'yotze, but
if he was dragging David's wallet out of David's house and he
hasn't yet picked it up, he hasn't yet stolen it, and only
when he leaves David's property and then brings it into רשות הרבים
reshut harabim at that moment when he's being מחלל שבת, mechallel Shabbat,
that's the moment that he's stealing it also. The גמרא Gemara has
that he puts his hand down and he pushes it into his
hand in רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So the fact that it's in
his hand means that he was stealing it and the fact, you
know, it wasn't on the ground, and the fact that it's in
רשות הרבים reshut harabim means that he just now did an act
of taking something into רשות הרבים. reshut harabim. So if it is
exactly at the same time he's exempt, שהרי איסור גניבה ואיסור סקילה
באים כאחד sheharei issur gneiva v'issur skila ba'im k'echad because the two...
comes at the exact same time: the stealing, the robbing, and the
stoning. So the גמרא Gemara says, so one minute, so why does
this work? Because according to, I mean, this is a support of
רב. Rav. It sounds like the wallet is still around and you
don't have to return it. So this really sounds like רב, Rav,
that when you say קים ליה kim lei you don't have to
return something. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what, והלכתא, v'hilchasa,
but the הלכה halacha is that we limit that case, even though
that sounds like a support of רב, Rav, in practice we limit
that ruling דשדינו בנהרא, dishadinu b'nahara, that the wallet has been thrown
into the ocean, the wallet is no longer around. If the wallet
were and the money's been spent, you know, if the wallet was
still around yet of course you have to return the wallet. So
exactly that case is the debate of רב Rav and רבא. Rava.
רב Rav would say you do not have to return the wallet,
even if it's around, and רבא Rava says no, when it says
you're exempt, it means you're exempt if it's no longer around and
you spent the money, but if it's still there you have to
give it back.
Yes, so he's giving up his life actually, in the previous case,
not giving up his life.
No, because even if there are no witnesses, even if it was
בשוגג, bishogeg, okay, that's what I said. קים ליה kim lei is
even if we're not going to execute you in practice. All right,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like, ah, so we have that
still debate between רב Rav and רבא, Rava, which is less of
a debate of בא במחתרת ba b'machteres and more of a debate
of a בבא קמא Bava Kama debate about what is the obligation
of a גנב ganav as the moment the גנב ganav steals it,
does he own it and just owes money, or does he at
the moment he steals it he has an obligation to give it
back and if he can't give it back then he owes money.
Okay, so it's really a בבא קמא Bava Kama debate. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so whenever anybody's learning בבא קמא, Bava Kama, they
wind up learning this עמוד amud in the גמרא Gemara in סנהדרין.
Sanhedrin. So the גמרא Gemara says, now here's a story. רבא איגנבו
ליה דיכרי במחתרתא. Rava ignavu lei dichrei b'machterta. So the same רבא
Rava had, what would be the chances, had rams stolen from him
through a tunnel. Like that would be amazing, like really? People were
really digging tunnels, okay, maybe. One minute, one minute. ואהדרינהו ניהליה, v'ahadrinhu
nihaleh, and then the גנבים, ganavim, they were, they had remorse. It
was ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur and they came and they
said, you know what, here take your rams back.
ולא קבלינהו. v'lo kablinhu. He said no, I'm not going to take
them. Why? אמר חובה נפיק מפומיה דרב. Amar hova nafik mipumei d'Rav.
Even though I think רב Rav is completely off-base here and I
think that you are obligated to give them back, I so revere
the ruling of רב, Rav, and even though it's my own property,
I will not accept them back. Okay, because according to רב, Rav,
you don't owe them back to me. Now תוספות Tosafos says it's
all very nice that they don't legally own it, they have to
give it back according to רב. Rav. But the גמרא Gemara still
says whenever we say קים ליה, kim lei, there's an obligation לצאת
ידי שמים, latzes yedei shamayim, you know, in order to do what
like in God's law you're still obligated to pay it back even
though the court won't make you. So why didn't he accept it?
So take a look, a little look at this תוספות. Tosafos. ולא
קבלינהו חובה נפיק מפומיה דרב. v'lo kablinhu hova nafik mipumei d'Rav. תימא,
Teima, המחיוב לצאת ידי שמים, hamichuyav latzes yedei shamayim, they have an
obligation to give it back even with a קים ליה kim lei
context, you know, to do their you know, the moral right thing.
אכדאמר Akd'amar בפרק הגוזל קמא ובבבא בתרא. b'perek HaGoizel Kama u'v'Bava Basra.
חסרון פרוטה דאשבה. Hisron pruta d'ashbah. התם אנסו אפילו באלימא. Hasam ansu
afilu b'alima. Anyway, whatever, we don't have to talk about that. ויש
לומר V'yesh lomar דכאן לא היו רוצים להחזיר אלא אם כן יתחייבו
בדיני אדם. d'kan lo hayu rotzim l'hachzir ela im kein yischayvu b'dinei
adam. They said we're giving it back to you because we because
we know we are legally obligated to give it back to you.
So רבא Rava said no, I don't want to take it because
according to רב Rav you're not legally obligated. I disagree with רב,
Rav, but whatever. If you only want to give it back because
you want to do what you're legally obligated to do, I won't
take it. If you want to give it back even if you're
not legally obligated because you want to do the right thing, then
fine I will take it. That's at least the way תוספות Tosafos
explains that. But that's important to appreciate that there's a difference between
your legal obligation and your moral obligation here. Okay. All right. So
that's the end of that debate which as I said is more
of a debate of a גנב, ganav, of a you know of
like a בבא קמא Bava Kama debate, not a debate of בא
במחתרת. ba b'machteres. Okay. But but obviously we're working within the normal
ways we would operate with normal laws of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה.
kim lei b'drabba minei. Which again to go back to my introduction,
raises the question, are we expanding the laws of קים ליה בדרבה
מיניה kim lei b'drabba minei to apply to cases of non-court imposed
punishments, or are we conceptualizing the right of self-defense as a type
of a court-imposed punishment at the moment, not one that would take
place afterwards. All right. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Our rabbis taught. Everybody
good? Ready? Yep, new topic. Or whatever, not really. אין לו דמים.
Ein lo damim. There's אם זרחה השמש עליו, im zarcha hashemesh alav,
okay, if the sun shines on him then there is no דמים,
damim, then there's no blood being spilled. Which means it's permissible to
kill him. וכי השמש עליו בלבד זרחה? V'chi hashemesh alav bilvad zarcha?
What, you know, it's like what what there's a phrase out of
English, you know, this person like thinks the sun shines, whatever, etc.,
etc. Anyway, do you think the sun shines only on him? Right?
מהו אם זרחה השמש עליו? Mah hu im zarcha hashemesh alav? Okay.
אלא אם ברור לך הדבר כשמש שאין לו שלום עמך, Ela im
barur l'cha hadavar k'shemesh she'ein lo shalom imach, הרגהו. hargehu. If it's
clear to you, as clear as the sun, as clear as daylight,
that he has no compassion on you and would be prepared to
kill you, then you kill him. ואם לאו אל תהרגו. V'im lav
al tahargehu. But if not, if there's a doubt, you don't have
a right to kill him. Which is interesting cause right, normally we
assume the right of self-defense, like you have to act to protect
your own life, so in cases of doubt you protect yourself. This
is...
those two phrases of יש לו דמים yesh lo damim and אין
לו דמים, ein lo damim, right? אם זרחה השמש. im zarcha hashemesh.
אין לו דמים אם זרחה השמש, ein lo damim im zarcha hashemesh,
אם זרחה השמש דמים לו. im zarcha hashemesh damim lo. And זרחה
השמש zarcha hashemesh we're saying means that things are black and are
clear to you. So one way we read it is, only if
it's clear to you do you have a right to kill him.
Now we're going to read it, only if it's clear to you
that he is not going to kill you, are you not allowed
to kill him. So does it have to be clear to you
that he's going to kill you and then you're allowed to kill
him, or are you always allowed to kill him
unless it's clear to you that he's not going to kill you?
There's that whole gray area in the middle.
Very difficult moment.
Right, of course. What are you going to do? Right. So let's
continue to read it.
It's a tunnel, right? It can be like just in secrecy, it
doesn't have to be...
no,
well we're going to expand it to, it's not limited to a
literal מחתרת. machteiret. But it's understood to be... the פסוקים psukim are
read literally, but the הלכה halacha doesn't limit it to the literal
case. Okay,
so that's the whole point of... I don't know about modern Hebrew,
but the whole point is, you're in the tunnel, the sun isn't
shining on you. You're, you know, once you exit the tunnel, וזרחה
השמש, v'zarcha hashemesh, that the sun shines on you, which means the
פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, you're already stolen and then you're
running away. At that stage you don't have a right to kill
him, that's פשט pshat of the פסוקים. psukim. Okay, anyway.
So it says like this, ותניא אידך, v'tanya idach, so one ברייתא
braita is only when it's clear your life is at risk, you
know, that he's planning to kill you, do you have a right
to kill him. But ותניא אידך, v'tanya idach, another ברייתא braita teaches,
אם זרחה השמש עליו דמים לו. im zarcha hashemesh alav damim lo.
וכי השמש עליו בלבד זרחה, v'chi hashemesh alav bilvad zarcha, what, it
shines only on you? But now it's tying it to the second
part of the פסוק. pasuk. אלא אם ברור לך כשמש שיש לו
שלום עמך, ela im barur lach keshemesh sheyesh lo shalom imach, oh
if it's clear to you that there's peace between you and that
at the end of the day you're friends and he wouldn't kill
you, if you know he won't kill you, אל תהרגהו, al tahargehu,
don't kill him, then דמים לו. damim lo. ואם לאו, v'im lav,
but if there's any doubt about it, then הרגהו, hargehu, you have
a right to kill him to protect yourself. So we've got a
big question, what do you do with this huge gray area in
the middle? קשיא סתמא אסתמא, kashya stama astama, we have a problem
of the סתמא stama of both of these of these two ברייתות.
braitot. לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
This is going to be interesting. כאן באב על הבן כאן בבן
על האב. kan b'av al haben kan b'ven al ha'av. Is the
father... this is the גמרא Gemara so deep in terms of understanding
these psychological issues about parents and kids... is the case that a
father is coming to steal from his son or son coming to
steal from his father? The גמרא Gemara basically says if a father
is coming to steal from his son, then we have to assume
that he would never like, you know, kill his son.
So the only time the son would be allowed to use lethal
force to protect himself is when it was clear to him that
the father was ready to kill him. But otherwise, so that's the
meaning of only if it's clear to you are you allowed to
actually use lethal force. That's in a case of a father and
a son because the father and a son we assume that unless
it's a real exception he would never be prepared to kill a
son. However, the son on the father, you know, plenty of cases
where children, you know,
kill parents for a whole variety of reasons. So if it's the
case of the son on the father, then we have to assume
that he totally would be prepared to kill the father and the
only time that the father is not allowed to use lethal force
to protect himself is if it's black and white to him that
the son would not be prepared to kill him. Okay, so the
upshot of all of that is, it's got a little bit confusing,
but besides the insight that a father would never kill his son
except in a rare exception and a son you don't need it
to be such a rare exception, that's very comforting, anyway, besides that
psychological insight, the upshot of all of that is if there's any
doubt protect your own life. The only times when we say, you
know, you have to be sure before you use lethal force is
a case which we start by saying we can totally assume that
this person would never, you know, want to kill you. If that's
the point of departure, that the גנב ganav would never want to
kill the בעל הבית, ba'al habayit, then you have to be sure
that it's a different case before you use lethal force. But in
every standard case we assume that the גנב ganav is going to
be even a case of a son on a father, even, we
assume that the גנב ganav is prepared to use lethal force and
therefore even if you don't... in any case of doubt protect your
own life. Okay, so the upshot is if there's any doubt, act
in self-defense. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
אמר רב, amar Rav, כל דאתי עלי
במחתרת, kol d'ati alai b'machteiret, anybody who would be... who would come
through a tunnel and come to steal from me, קטלינא ליה, katlina
lei, I'd kill anybody, anybody in this בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, if
I see you coming out of that tunnel I'm... I'm going to
assume you're ready to take my life and therefore I would kill
you in self-defense. לבר מיוני בר קניס libar mi-Yoni bar Kenis ורב
חנינא בר שילא. ve-Rav Chanina bar Shila. Him I wouldn't kill if
he came out of the tunnel. So by why the why, this
certainly got the attention of the תלמידים talmidim I face. אילימא משום
דצדיק הוא, eileima mishum de-tzadik hu, ah he's righteous, he would never
use lethal force. What do you mean? הכא במחתרתא, hacha be-mach-tarsa, he's
coming out of the tunnel! So it doesn't matter, which is really
very profound, right, about issues about character, especially thinking about it on
Yom Kippur or whatever. Like, I could know somebody that I know
that they're normally such a righteous person, but now I see them
doing this act, whatever desperation drove them to this, I can't assume
that the normal character that I've been familiar with is going to
continue to hold. And if he's willing to do this act of
desperation, you know, whatever I knew about him in the past, I
have to think that he's prepared to use lethal force. Okay, even
if he was a צדיק tzadik before this. אלא משום דקים לי
בגויה דמרחם עלי כרחם אב על הבן. ella mishum de-kim li be-gaveih
de-meracheim alai ke-racheim av al ha-ben. Okay, that's actually harking about Yom
Kippur, right? כרחם אב על הבן, ke-racheim av al ha-ben, right? רחמנא
כרחם, rachamana ke-racheim, right? Like a father has compassion on a son.
Okay, so I know that he has so much love for me,
it's the love a father would have for a son and that
no matter how desperate he would be, no matter how much he
was driven to ignore, you know, any sort of principles of morality.
Like, it's interesting, morality operates different than relationships, right? A person could
be a complete prepared to do murder, but not somebody that they
really love and care for. Okay? So it's like, so yes, maybe
somebody could be a צדיק, tzadik, now they're coming out of the
tunnel I have to think they're a רשע rasha and that they're
prepared to kill me. But somebody I know has that much love
for me, like a father has love for a son, him I
wouldn't—I know that he is would not be prepared to kill me
and I would not use lethal force. Okay? So it's a nice
illustration of the idea of אב על הבן, av al ha-ben, but
also an illustration of the point that you basically, except for very
rare exceptions, have to assume that anybody, no matter what you knew
about them in the past, you know, if they're coming out of
the tunnel and they've gone to that degree, do what you need
to do to protect your life, your life is at risk. Okay?
So now the גמרא Gemara continues: תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis
taught.
דמים לו בין בחול בין בשבת. damim lo bein be-chol bein be-Shabbos.
Okay, when he is, it's blood when you're not allowed to kill
him, whether it's a weekday or שבת, Shabbos, you can't kill him.
אין לו דמים, ein lo damim, you're allowed to kill him, בין
בחול בין בשבת, bein be-chol bein be-Shabbos, whether it's weekday or whatever,
you're allowed to use self-defense to protect yourself. Like, "Oh no, I
can't defend my own life because the גנב ganav is מוקצה." muktzah.
No, no, no, no, no.
You do what you have to do to protect your own life,
even on שבת. Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says like, בשלמא אין
לו דמים, bishlama ein lo damim, I get the case when the
guy has no blood, you're allowed to act in self-defense, בין בחול
בין בשבת, bein be-chol bein be-Shabbos, you're telling me whether a weekday
or שבת, Shabbos, it's true, you have to tell me that. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, salca da’atach amina, now here gets back to the point
I was saying before, listen to what the הוה אמינא hava amina
was, not that the גנב ganav is מוקצה, muktzah, but סלקא דעתך
אמינא מידי דהוה אהרוגי בית דין. salca da’atach amina midi de-havei a-harugei
beis din. Maybe we should treat it like we treat court-imposed executions,
דבשבת לא קטלינן להו. de-be-Shabbos lo katlinan lehu. You don't execute criminals
on שבת. Shabbos. So I can't execute this guy who's coming to
rob from me on שבת. Shabbos. That is a crazy הוה אמינא
hava amina because the thing that the motivating thing here is self-defense,
right? But the fact that the גמרא Gemara has this הוה אמינא
hava amina means that even when it's being at least at this
stage the גמרא Gemara thinks, I would have thought that even when
it's being motivated by self-defense and that's what sort of authorizes this
action, we conceptualize it as a—as you are acting on behalf of
the court and imposing a punishment on this guy and therefore maybe
you're not allowed to do it on שבת. Shabbos. Okay,
so therefore קא משמע לן דקטלינן, ka-mashma lan de-katlinan, that nevertheless you
kill him. Now the question always is when you move from the
הוה אמינא hava amina to the קא משמע לן, ka-mashma lan, how
much do you retain of the assumptions of the הוה אמינא? hava
amina? Is the קא משמע לן ka-mashma lan we got it totally
wrong? It has nothing to do with court-imposed punishments, it's all just
about self-defense and that's why you can do it on שבת? Shabbos?
Or do we say no, we still conceptualize it as a court-imposed
punishment, but here it's a court-imposed punishment that we do on שבת
Shabbos because we have to do it on שבת Shabbos because we
have to save this guy's life? Right? So it's not clear how
much it's shifting, but it certainly puts out as a הוה אמינא
hava amina to conceptualize this as a type of a court-imposed punishment.
Okay, that's why it had to tell me you do it on
שבת. Shabbos. אלא דמים לו בין בחול בין בשבת, ella damim lo
bein be-chol bein be-Shabbos, when you don't kill him, when it's some
case where you know that your life isn't at risk and you're
not allowed to kill him, whether on a weekday or שבת. Shabbos.
So השתא בחול לא קטלינן ליה, hashta be-chol lo katlinan leh, so
בשבת מבעיא? be-Shabbos mibaya? Like, of course if you weren't allowed to
kill him on a Wednesday, so
בשבת מבעיא? be-Shabbos mibaya? Like, why does it have to tell me
that? אמר רב ששת: amar rav sheshes: no, לא נצרכה אלא לפקח
עליו את הגל. lo nitzrecha ella le-fakei'ach alav es ha-gal. No,
no, no, no, no. Here's what it's telling me: The guy broke
into the—through the tunnel, okay, and it was a case I don't
know, an אב על הבן, av al ha-ben, or somebody who so
loved me that I knew would never kill me, okay, but they
were still coming to rob from me on שבת Shabbos and they
dug the whole tunnel on שבת, Shabbos, they were מחלל שבת, mechaleil
Shabbos, they dug the tunnel the whole thing, but they weren't prepared
to kill me, and then the tunnel collapsed on them. Do I
have to save the guy's life? And the answer is yes. It
doesn't matter what terrible things that that person was doing just up
until that moment, okay? Even on שבת. Shabbos. Now so יש לו
דמים yesh lo damim is, meaning the point it's saying is, not
only יש לו דמים yesh lo damim you're not allowed to murder
him, יש לו דמים yesh lo damim he has not, he still
is a living person who has a right to his life. And
if the and if the tunnel collapsed on him, you have an
obligation to save his life. Okay, so on the one hand that's
very powerful. The same guy who a minute ago was going to
rob me blind and was מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos to dig this
tunnel, I have to save his life now that the tunnel collapsed,
even if it means me being מחלל שבת. mechallel Shabbos. Okay, however,
you understand that there's an implicit flip side of this which רש״י
Rashi says explicitly. If he was being prepared to kill me, I
wouldn't have to save his life when the tunnel collapsed on him.
Now that's very interesting. That even though I could have taken his
life, now that the tunnel collapsed on him, the threat has been
neutralized, right, my life is no longer at risk. So once my
life is no longer at risk, why do I not have to
now try to save his life? He's a human being, right, his
my life isn't at risk right now, okay, he was doing a
terrible thing a minute ago. So רש״י Rashi makes it sound like,
well, once he basically forfeited his life, you know, that's the אין
לו דמים, ein lo damim, you have no obligation now to save
his life on שבת. Shabbos. But it's hard for me to understand
that, right, like why should that be true? Again, if we think
of it as like a court imposed punishment, maybe you could sort
of see him as like he's somebody deserving of death and therefore
why should I now be מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbos to save his
life? But it was just to protect myself, once the threat's neutralized
it's hard to understand that. Yes, Jenna.
I feel like it's more like you're not obligated to like revive
him so that then maybe he'll kill you again, right?
Like if that we assume that that's the case that if I
were to save his life, you know, with the big pile of
stones on him once I get the pile of stones off, presumably
he's not going to present it anymore. רש״י Rashi does not say
because there's a continued threat. רש״י Rashi just says since he was
prepared to kill me, so therefore he has basically forfeited his life,
that's the phrase אין לו דמים, ein lo damim, and therefore he's
already like a dead man, dead man walking, and I don't have
an obligation to do anything for him on שבת, Shabbos, which is
a very, you know, strange idea I think. Anyway, so let's keep
on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay now,
okay,
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our rabbis taught, והוכה ומת, vehuka vamet, he
smit and he dies, אין לו דמים, ein lo damim, so I
the there was no blood, there was no act of murder committed
there, it was an act of self defense בכל אדם, bechol adam,
whoever goes ahead and kills him, this is important, it's not only
I have a right to self defense, somebody else who's seeing can
act to intervene and to save my life, which is what the
next משנה Mishna is going to focus on. ומת vamet and he's
and he's killed בכל מיתה שאתה יכול להמיתו, bechol mita she'ata yachol
lehamito, whatever type of act you have to use to neutralize him
and to kill him. Okay, בשלמא והוכה בכל אדם אצטריך, Bishlama vehuka
bechol adam itzterich, so the גמרא Gemara says, I understand why you
have to bring other people into it, what's that teaching me? סלקא
דעתך אמינא בעל הבית הוא דקים ליה ואין אדם מעמיד עצמו על
ממונו, Salka da'atach amina ba'al habayis hu dekim lei v'ein adam ma'amid
atzmo al mamono, for the בעל הבית ba'al habayis we say that
when I that I have a right of self defense because he
was prepared to kill me, he knew that I was going to
come to defend myself and he was prepared to kill me. אבל
אחר לא, aval acher lo, he wasn't prepared to kill any of
you guys, so what so since your life isn't at risk, what
entitles you to intervene? Meaning, to this telling you an important point,
it's not only the person whose life is at risk is entitled,
it's anybody can act to save that person's life. קא משמע לן
דרודף הוא, ka mashma lan derodef hu, it's not just because your
life was the one that was at you have a right to
save your own life, self defense. No, this guy is running to
is like, you know, pursuing to and prepared to get is in
the pursuit of trying to commit murder, ואפילו אחר נמי לא, v'afilu
acher nami lo, and as we're going to see in the next
משנה, Mishna, anybody can intervene to save a potential victim. So it
is not just the right of self defense, it is the right
or the obligation to intervene to save a victim. I should say
right because it's also like, you know, as I mentioned before, an
obligation to intervene. Okay, תוספות Tosafos actually I think said no, anyway,
an earlier תוספות Tosafos sort of made that point that it's not
just that other people I have a right, you have a right,
we all have an obligation to intervene to protect anybody's life who's
at risk or my own life that's at risk. There's an interesting
debate I should say though in the אחרונים, acharonim, which is like
all things when you're like allowed to do something, the general question
is do we say הותרה hutra or דחויה? dechuya? Like when you're
allowed to violate שבת Shabbos to save a life, do we sort
of say yes, you're violating it but it's allowed? Or do we
say no, fundamentally it's not a violating of שבת? Shabbos? So there's
a little bit of that question by the case of רודף, rodef,
who basically say it's permitted for me like to, you know, kill
this guy to because to save the life, but it's like a
דחויה, dechuya, like it it pushes off the prohibitions of murder, but
or do we fundamentally say like הותרה, hutra, which is like אין
לו דמים? ein lo damim? It's completely, you know, not even considered
an act of not like justified manslaughter, it wasn't manslaughter at all,
אין לו דמים. ein lo damim. Okay, and to some degree what's
the נפקא מינה nafka mina of that? So to some degree they
want to say this question about like, you know, to what degree
the other issue that's not being explicitly discussed here, to what degree
do I have to sort of sort of, you know, seriously try
to neutralize him in a way other like יכול להצילו באחד מאבריו?
yachol lehatzilo be'echad me'evarav? So one of the אחרונים acharonim suggests that
for an outsider you're held to a higher standard of
יכול להציל. yachol lehatzil. I don't have to start to, right? So
anyway, that's like an interesting way of sort of seeing some difference
between the person himself or the person who's intervening.
Anyway, is there a danger to yourself in terms of the obligation
to save somebody's life?
Oh, that's a very good question. In general, the question is, whether
it's the case of רודף rodef or the case of a burning
building, right? If I have an obligation to act to save somebody
whose life is at risk, right, how much do I have to
put my own life at risk? Okay, do I have to run
into a burning building to save the child if I might get
myself killed in the process? Okay, so the general assumption is that
you do not have to put your life at risk. Now, what
degree of risk? Does it mean zero risk? Does it mean, you
know, whatever? Let's say I'm not risking my life, but I'm risking
getting burned and badly, right? So that's a really good question. Like,
mostly מצוות mitzvot don't obligate you to risk your life, but some
מצוות, mitzvot, their very nature obligates you to. Like the מצוה mitzvah
to go to war obligates you to risk your life, right? So
is the מצוה mitzvah to save a life at risk, how much
is that demanding of you is a great question, which is discussed
in the אחרונים. acharonim. Is it okay? That's a great question. All
right, let's try to read a little bit more. Okay, so that's,
we've now introduced the important principle of not just self-defense, others have
to intervene as well. Okay, but אלא ומת בכל מיתה שיכול להמיתו,
ela v'met b'chol mita she'yachol l'hamiso, but when it says he dies
and you can use any way to kill him, למה לי? lama
li? Why do you have to tell me that? מרצח נפקא. Me-rotzeach
nafka. I already know it from executing a murderer. דתניא, Detanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, baraita, מות יומת המכה רצח הוא, mot yumat
hamakeh rotzeach hu, he will be put to death, he's a murderer.
This is the court-imposed punishment. אין לי אלא במיתה האמורה בו. Ein
li ela b'mita ha'amura bo. I only know that you can execute
a murderer with the court, with the official execution, like, which is,
what do you call it, which is by the sword. ומנין שאם
אתה יכול להמיתו במיתה הכתובה בו שאם אי אתה יכול להמיתו במיתה
הכתובה בו שאתה רשאי להמיתו בכל מיתה שאתה יכול להמיתו? U-minayin she'im
ata yachol l'hamiso b'mita haktuvah bo, she'im i ata yachol l'hamiso b'mita
haktuvah bo, she'ata rashai l'hamiso b'chol mita she'ata yachol l'hamiso? How do
I know if for whatever reason he's run out of prison, he's
escaped, he's gonna make a grunt for it, whatever, we can't for
some reason do the standard execution, how do we know we have
a license to execute him in whatever way possible? תלמוד לומר מות
יומת. Talmud lomar mot yumat. He shall surely be put to death,
מכל מקום. mi-kol makom. So once you know you're allowed to do
that by executing a murderer, you should certainly be allowed to do
that, we should be able to apply that and say that you
can do this during this act of self-defense.
Again notice that the גמרא Gemara is talking about this as if
this was a court-imposed punishment. We know one court-imposed punishment you can
do anything, so in this case also you should be able to
do anything. Right, the real point should be of course you should
be able to do anything, you've got to save the guy's life.
Right? It's not about learning from some הלכה halacha of court-imposed punishment.
So it's very telling that the גמרא Gemara is making that comparison.
Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says no, I wouldn't have learned from
that case. מכל מקום שאני התם דאמר קרא מות יומת. Mi-kol makom
shani hatam de'amar kra mot yumat. No, maybe it's a special exception,
only by a murderer are you entitled to execute him other ways,
maybe here you're not. גמרא Gemara says one minute, ונגמר מיניה? v'nigmar
mineh? Why not use that as a principle, apply it more generally?
משום דהוי רצח
וגואל הדם שני כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין
מלמדים. Mishum de'havay rotzeach v'goal hadam shne ketuvim haba'im k'echad v'chol shne
ketuvim haba'im k'echad ein m'lamdim. No, because we also know from the
case of the גואל הדם, goal hadam, right, that he's, you know,
that it also can do any form of executing if it's not
the one that the תורה Torah prescribes. So, therefore, I might say
that those are the exception, not the rule. Now, the גואל הדם
goal hadam is not a court-imposed execution, right? That's somebody acting, you
know, to take vengeance or whatever. So already we're broadening it. But
again, it is still very interesting that the גמרא Gemara sort of
doesn't sort of, you know, says like, like, as I would have
had a reasonable הוה אמינא hava amina that you cannot do anything,
anything you're allowed to save your life, maybe only הכאה, hakaa, maybe
only some type of smiting, something else that you might have had
to do, you would not be allowed to do. Okay, and I
couldn't have learned from רצח, rotzeach, and therefore the פסוק pasuk had
to tell me מכל מקום. mi-kol makom. Again, that seems to be
saying that it's not that the overriding point is do whatever you
need to be, at least the הוה אמינא hava amina was not
just about protecting the life. The הוה אמינא hava amina was seeing
it more in the context of a type of a court-imposed punishment
and maybe therefore what you have license to do is more limited.
Okay, and the קא משמע לן ka mashma lan is no, you
have, you can do whatever you need to. Is that still seeing
it as a court-imposed punishment or is that seeing it completely outside
the court? That's not clear. Okay, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, now it's
already 8:32, I don't know, should we, do people give me like
five more minutes so we can try to finish the דף? daf?
Okay. תנו רבנן מחתרת. tanu rabanan machtoret. אין לי אלא מחתרת. Ein
li ela machtoret. Here you go, Micah. I only know a tunnel.
גגו חצרו וקפיפו מנין? Gago chatzer v'kafifa minayin? How do I know
if he comes through your roof or your yard or whatever? תלמוד
לומר ימצא הגנב מכל מקום. Talmud lomar yimatze hganav mi-kol makom. However
he's found, however he breaks in. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר מחתרת?
Im ken ma talmud lomar machtoret? So why does it say a
tunnel? מפני שרוב גנבים מצויין במחתרת. Mipnei she'rov ganavim imtzuyin b'machtoret. Not
to tell you any הלכה, halacha, just, you know, that's the normal
case. תניא אידך מחתרת, Tanya idach machtoret, אין לי אלא. ein li
ela. גג חצר ואכסדרה מנין *gag chatzer veachsadra minayin* תלמוד לומר *talmud
lomar* אם ימצא הגנב *im yimatzei haganav* מכל מקום *mikol makom*. Fine,
however he comes, breaks in. אם כן *Im kein* מה תלמוד לומר
*mah talmud lomar* במחתרת *bemachteret*? So why does it say tunnel? מחתרתו
זו היא התראתו *Machterato zo hi hatraato* because by the case of
the tunnel, the tunnel is his warning. Now what does that mean?
So what רש"י *Rashi* says here it means is that if you're
going to be to the extent of digging the tunnel, then we
assume that you're prepared to use lethal force. If you just broke
in through a window or through coming down the roof, we're not
going to assume you're prepared to use lethal force. Okay. Now if
you're carrying a gun, right, they didn't have guns, right? So there
they had to use other circumstances to show though the guy could
have had a, whatever, a knife, right? Whatever. But the point is,
it's not that it's limited only to the tunnel, but the tunnel
is basically it's limited to cases where we can assume the guy
is prepared to. So this is not just what's the relationship between
them what we discussed before, here's another important point. If he just
broke in through the back door, we don't assume he's going unless
there's other indications, we don't assume he's going to use lethal force.
Only when he's breaking through, he's like he's going to the extent
of digging the tunnel, then he's really prepared to do anything. Okay.
So that's מחתרתו זו היא התראתו *machterato zo hi hatraato*.
If you look at רש"י *Rashi*, זו היא התראתו *zo hi hatraato*,
the first wide line, שאין צריך התראה אחרת אלא הורגו מיד דכיון
דטרח ומסר נפשו לחתור אדעתא דהכי אתא דיהי קטיל אפי קטלינן ליה
והוה כטור כיון דרודף הוא אין צריך התראה אלא מצילין אותו בנפשו
*sheein tzarich hatraa acheret ela horgo miyad dikeivan detarach umasar nafsho lachtor
adaata dehachi ata deyehi katil api katlinan lei vehavei kator keivan derodef
hu ein tzarich hatraa ela matzilin oto benafsho*. Look, meaning the התראה
*hatraa* is you don't need התראה *hatraa*. Once we see that he's
about to commit murder, you do what you need to to protect
yourself. אבל נכנס לחצר וגג דרך הפתח אין הורגו *Aval nichnas lachatzer
vegag derech hapetach ein horgo*. Until, now here's the question, here I
said until let's say he's carrying a gun. But look what רש"י
*Rashi* says. עד שיתרו בו בעדים *Ad sheyitru bo beeidim*. What would
when would I be allowed to protect myself if somebody broke into
my back door with lethal force? If I gave him התראה *hatraa*
with witnesses. חזי *Chazei*, look, דקיימנא באפך *dekayimna beapach*, you should know,
I am prepared to stand against you, okay, וקטלינן לך
*vekatlinan lach*, and I will kill you if you try to take
my property. וזה יקבל עליו התראה *Veze yakabel alav hatraa* and this
person has to accept the התראה *hatraa* ויאמר יודע אני *veyomar yodeia
ani*, I know that you are prepared to kill me, ועל מנת
כן אני עושה *veal menat kein ani oseih*, and I'm coming here
with this intent. Wait a minute, let me get a lawyer so
we can, whatever, to call, okay, get the whole thing down. תם
אתם אבוא ואהרוג אותך *Tam atem avo veaharog otcha*, I will kill
you. אבל בלא התראה לא *Aval belo hatraa lo*. Now what does
that whole sound like that רש"י *Rashi* just described? Classic התראה *hatraa*
that you give in order to entitle a court to execute. I
have to have witnesses, I have to warn you, you have to
know what you're doing, you have to accept what you're doing. So
again, רש"י *Rashi* is bringing in and seeing this as a type
of a court imposed punishment. Okay, although obviously what would be easier
to say without רש"י *Rashi* is if I warn you and say
like, in cases where it's clear because I'm ready to defend myself
with lethal force or whatever, it's clear by what's going on that
you're prepared to kill me, then even if you just broke in
my back door, I'm allowed to use lethal force. Okay, but anyway
in the case of the tunnel, רש"י *Rashi* seems to say there
he's a רודף *rodef* and you don't need התראה *hatraa*, but in
the case of breaking in the back door, that's more like not
a רודף *rodef* but we can turn it into a court imposed
punishment if he accepts התראה *hatraa*. Like two models going on here.
Okay, very interesting. All right, let's read a little bit more.
This is going to be, I mean this is really important, I
really want to finish דף *daf*, but it's such, such, so important,
we're going to end here, okay, and we will pick up with
this tomorrow.